Antoine C. Petit

Current position

Postdoctoral researcher at Lund University

Contact

Sölvegatan 27 223 62 Lund Sweden

+33 6 76 74 99 61

apetit[at]astro.lu.se

www.astro.lu.se/~apetit github.com/acpetit

- ORCID -

0000-0003-1970-1790

- Nationality -French

Languages

French - native English - fluent Spanish - medium Swedish – beginner

Programming

- HPC -

C++ & OpenMP Fortran

- Data analysis -

Python Jupyter, numpy Julia, Matlab

- General skills -

Linux, git, bash, LTFX

Research interests

My research focuses on planet dynamics, particularly in the context of planet formation and close to instability systems. I use analytical and numerical methods to understand how planet interactions shape exoplanetary system architecture. I also have applied my theoretical skills in the context of specific planetary systems in order to understand their history.

Research experience

2019-2021	Postdoctoral researcher Collaborators: A. Johansen, M. Lambrechts. Postdoctor tional and theoretical astronomy.	und Observatory, Lund, Sweden al fellowship in observa-
2016-2019	Post-graduate research "Architecture and stability of planetary systems", Supervisors: Jacques Laskar and Gwenaël Boué.	Paris Observatory, Paris, France
2016	Master thesis in astrophysics "First order mean motion overlap in planetary systems", Supervisor: Jacques Laskar.	Paris Observatory, Paris, France
2015	Master thesis in mathematics "Herman resonance in the three-body problem in four dime Supervisor: Jacques Féjoz.	ENS, Paris, France ensions",
2014	Research internship (6 months) "Mixing and transport of metals by turbulence in galactic d	UCSC, California, USA

Supervisors: Mark Krumholz and Doug Lin.

Education

2016 – 2019	PhD in Astrophysics Title: "Architecture and stability of planetary systems", Supervisors: Jacques Laskar and Gwenaël Boué. Defended the 28th of June 2019.	Paris Observatory, France	
2016	Diploma of the École Normale Supérieure (ENS) Most selective research focused university in France. Specialization in Physics and Mathematics.	ENS, Paris, France	
2016	Master degree in Theoretical Physics Specialization in celestial mechanics, statistical physics & g	ervatoy & UPMC, Paris, France general relativity.	
2015	Master degree in Mathematics Specialization in dynamical systems and differential geome	ENS, & UPMC, Paris, France etry.	
2013	Bachelor degree, Physics	ENS, Paris, France	
2012	Accepted 9 th at the ENS after competitive exam. Physics department.		
2010 – 2012	Preparatory school in MPSI/MP* Two-year intensive program in advanced mathematics and national competitive exams for entry to engineering schools.		
2010	French Science Baccalauréat (High school diploma)	Grenoble, France	

Publications

8 publications (6 as first author). 126 citations, h-index of 5. See the complete list on NASA/ADS.			
2020	The path to instability in compact multi-planetary systems A. C. Petit, G. Pichierri, M. B. Davies, A. Johansen	A&A, 641, A176	
2020	Resonance in the K2-19 system is at odds with its high reported eccentricities A. C. Petit, E. A. Petigura, M. B. Davies, A. Johansen	MNRAS, 496, 3	
2019	High-order regularised symplectic integrator for collisional planetary systems A. C. Petit , J. Laskar, G. Boué & M. Gastineau	A&A, 628, A32	
2019	Nearly Polar orbit of the sub-Neptune HD3167 c: Constraints on a multi-planet sical history S. Dalal, G. Hébrard, A. Lecavelier, A. C. Petit, et al.	System dynam -A&A, 631, A28	
2018	Hill stability in the AMD framework A. C. Petit, J. Laskar & G. Boué	A&A, 617, A93	
2017	AMD-stability in the presence of first-order mean motion resonances A. C. Petit, J. Laskar & G. Boué	A&A, 607, A35	
2017	AMD-stability and the classification of planetary systems J. Laskar & A. C. Petit	A&A, 605, A72	
2015	Mixing of metals by gravitational instability-driven turbulence in galactic discs A. C. Petit, M. Krumholz, N. Goldbaum & J. Forbes	MNRAS, 449, 3	
Role as a reviewer			

Role as a reviewer

2017 – Reviewed 10 articles for the leading international astronomy journals: Astronomy & Astrophysics, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Icarus, SIAM Journal on Applied Dynamical Systems.

Awards and funding

2019	Fysiografen grant : The Fund of the Walter Gyllenberg Foundation : 220,000 kr (21,000 €)
2016	PhD grant from the French government accorded by the ENS.
2012	4-year fellowship as a trainee civil servant at the ENS.

Presentations and Conferences

International conference presentations

	resentations are marked with a star *.	
2020	PLATO ESP workshop Spacing and stability of compacts systems	Online
2018	PLATO Theory Workshop Hill stability in the AMD framework	Cambridge, UK
2018	PNP prospective coloquium Hill stability in the AMD framework	Nice, France
2017 *	Exoplanets and Planet Formation AMD-stability and the classification of exoplanets	Shanghai, Chine
2017	CELMEC VII AMD-stability in the context of first-order MMRs	Viterbo, Italie

Seminars Dec. 2020	Exoplanets team seminar Resonance and dynamical constraints on the K2-19 system	IPAG, Grenoble, France
Nov. 2020	IPAG/IRAM Seminar Dynamical constraints on planetary systems architecture	Grenoble, France
Oct. 2019	Astronomy department seminar Architecture and stability of planetary systems	Lund, Suède
Jan. 2019	Planet formation meeting Dynamical constraints on planet formation	Lund, Suède
2018	ASD Team seminar Hill-stability in the AMD framework	Paris, France
2017	IMCCE Postdocs and PhD students seminar AMD-stability in the context of first-order MMRs	Paris, France
Conference committees		

Lund, Sweden

For All Meeting local organization committee

Teaching and Supervision

2020 – 2021	Teaching Assistant Stellar Structure and Evolution (Master), Topics in The students)	eoretical	Lund University, Sweden Astrophysics (PhD-
2020 – 2021	Master project supervisor Supervision of Kaltrina Kajtazi for a 1.5 year master pro Subject: Capture of planets into mean motion resonance		Lund University, Sweden
2019	Culture night outreach talk The moons of the Solar System		Lund University, Sweden
2018-2019	Teaching Assistant Exercises sessions of probabilities and Lebesgue integnours). Graded all written work, and final written exams	gration a	e University, Paris, France at Bachelor level (40
2013	Oral examiner Mathematics examiner in preparatory classes.	Lycée Lo	uis le Grand, Paris, France

Outreach

2019	Culture night outreach talk The moons of the Solar System	Lund University, Sweden
2017 – 2019	Introduction to astronomy for secondary school students Bi-annual intervention with a small group students asking of	Paris Observatory, France questions about my work
	and astronomy in general.	